Guide to the Frederick W. Beinecke Collector's Files
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Frederick W. Beinecke collector's files
1950-1971
WA MSS S-2760
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
9.25
(11 boxes)
The files consist of inventories and a card index for Frederick W. Beinecke's Western Americana collection. The collection documented in this material was donated to the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, chiefly between 1960 and 1971. The inventories (Series I.) document Frederick W. Beinecke's larger donations, including a collection on the Mexican War in 1960, a collection of printed material in 1962, and material donated at the time of his death in 1971. The card index (Series II.) documents Frederick W. Beinecke's acquisition of material in the 1950s and 1960s and includes documentation of provenance and acquisition, and descriptions provided by booksellers. The cards also include notes on handling of the material at Yale. The index cards informed the descriptions of material in catalog records in Yale University Library's catalog.
Beinecke, Frederick W.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Frederick W. Beinecke, 1960-1971.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 4-11 (card index): Formerly restricted until 2012.
Frederick W. Beinecke
Frederick W. Beinecke (1887-1971, Yale 1909S), collector of rare books and manuscripts, and major benefactor of the Yale Collection of Western Americana and the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library.
Scope and Contents
The files consist of inventories and a card index to Frederick W. Beinecke's Western Americana collection. The collection documented in this material was donated to the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, chiefly between 1960 and 1971. The inventories (Series I.) document Frederick W. Beinecke's larger donations, including a collection on the Mexican War in 1960, a collection of printed material in 1962, and material donated at the time of his death in 1971. The card index (Series II.) documents Frederick W. Beinecke's acquisition of material in the 1950s and 1960s and includes documentation of provenance and acquisition, and descriptions provided by booksellers. The cards also include notes on handling of the material at Yale. The index cards informed descriptions of material in catalog records in Orbis, Yale University Library's catalog.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Inventories, 1962-1971. II. Card Index, circa 1950-1962.
Academic libraries -- Collection development; Acquisition of manuscripts -- United States; Antiquarian booksellers -- United States; Book collectors -- United States; Booksellers and bookselling -- United States; Cataloging of manuscripts -- United States; Cataloging of rare books -- United States; Collection development (Libraries) -- United States; Libraries and booksellers -- United States; Manuscripts -- Collections; Manuscripts -- Collectors and collecting; Rare books -- Collectors and collecting; West (U.S.) -- History; Card files -- United States -- 20th Century; Antiquarian booksellers -- United States -- 20th Century; Book collectors -- United States -- 20th Century; Beinecke, Frederick W.
- Inventories, 1960-1971; Series I; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  - "The Mexican War Collection," typescript carbon, [1960] (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Catalogue of a collection of rare Western American books presented by Frederick W. Beinecke to the Yale University Library," typescript carbon with manuscript notes in an unidentified hand, 1962 December 6 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Catalogue of a collection of original historical manuscripts presented by Frederick W. Beinecke to the Yale University Library," typescript, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Library manuscript catalogue, carbons, undated (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
  - Printed books, original, A-L, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Printed books, original, M-Z, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - "Addition to Beinecke printed books catalogue", undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - "Western Americana Rare Books and Manuscripts Passing to Yale University under the will of Frederick W. Beinecke", 1971 July 30 (Box 3, Folder 9-10)
- Card Index, circa 1950-circa 1962; Series II; 8; (8 boxes)
  Organized under three headings: Author Index, Title Index, and Author Index (photocopy).
  - Author Index
    - A-D (Box 4)
    - E-L (Box 5)
    - Mc-T (Box 6)
    - U-Z (Box 7)
  - Title Index
    - A-C (Box 7)
    - D-Mem (Box 8)
    - Men-Sp (Box 9)
    - Sq-Z (Box 10)
  - Author Index (photocopy)
    - A-F (Box 10)
    - G-Z (Box 11)